hello barber and welcome to this gents
scissor cutting tutorial this is a
complete walkthrough from start to
finish covering a lot of different
techniques
but don't worry i've been barbering for
20 years and i'm here to guide you
through this chop so we're starting
right here right in the middle of the
head and a fundamental thing that you're
going to need to do when you're scissor
cutting is to wet the hair down you
should always wet the hair it gives you
great control of the hair
so what i'm going to do
is just separate this hair here at the
back above the occipital bone
now if i separate that there
it lets me have access to all these
sections that i want to cut further down
so with that out of the way
i'm going in with my scissor my very
first section is right on the occipital
bone and i'm picking it up with the
scissor
and then put placing the comb underneath
it i'm going to take many many sections
as i work my way down that area and the
reason is i want it to be as clean as
possible so lots of sections and little
sections
now as you get nearer the bottom you can
either lower the angle that you're
lifting the comb up at
or get slightly closer to the head and
this allows you to create a taper
now just look how much hair is actually
in the comb it's not very much and it's
easy for my scissors to cut through i'm
not going to be left with scissor marks
because of that
[Music]
jumping over the right hand side of that
we'll just do the same method
working our way straight down in
sections
there we go
not too much here now remember that just
a small amount of hair work your way
down
this comb i'm using by the way is a ys
park barbers comb now that comb has
white teeth and narrow teeth and for
this technique using the wide teeth is a
lot better
sometimes when your scissors are
overcoming if you're using the narrow
teeth the narrow teeth can't get into
the hair and sometimes they lift it up
so
using the white teeth is a lot easier
[Music]
okay left and right done let's just go a
little bit further over the left just
try and get closer to the ear now you'll
notice that i keep my comb well in front
of the ear
and that's a guard for the ear okay so
we're going in with a scissor and we
don't want to go anywhere near the ear
so
plastic in between the metal and the
skin
[Music]
right down at the very bottom take those
little hairs off
[Music]
important here make sure when you're
going in here that you get
the point of the scissor right in behind
the hairline
and that way we're picking up all the
hair
so you can see it there that little
point that i showed you
we'll just try we'll get the point in
and then lift up to the angle we want
[Music]
just a little bit of refinement here
sometimes i just like to just have a
quick double check and refine anything
okay let's pull down all that hair now
that was getting in the way before
and if we lift that up i'll be able to
see the short hair just at the end of my
fingertips and if i hold my fingers out
vertical i can just cut straight up from
there
that means that if i'm pulling my
fingers out straight the hair further up
is getting further away from the head
and that's graduating in a longer hair
so it's allowing me to
build up i'm working sort of short
working my way up in a longer hair
and that can allow the hair to be longer
on top it gives it some support
so i'll work all the way towards the ear
and then on the other side i'm going to
work all the way towards the ear as well
once i've done that
i'm happy that i've almost covered the
entire back section of this haircut and
i'm going to show you how we can join in
towards the front
[Music]
since we've cut the whole back of the
head that'll be our guide and we can use
that to work out the length to be
cutting the sides
[Music]
so if i put my scissor in here there's
the short hair from the back and i just
need to cut along the spine of my comb
and that'll ensure that i'm cutting to
the same length that i had the hair on
the back
now this technique this scissor over
comb i've said it before in previous
videos it really is an essential barber
technique
it takes a little bit of practice it's
the flipping of the comb here you flip
it over and under if you know what i
mean so under
flip it over and then comb the hair down
and then flip it under again
there we go now you'll notice on the ear
there again just keeping the comb on top
of the ear when i'm cutting because
let's not have any accidents
keep your cutting safe
but refinement here
and just down the very bottom come in
front of the ear again
okay now let's move over to the very
front of the side and i'll lift that up
there's the short hair that i'm always
looking for and cut to that
now you'll notice me what i'm going to
do in a second here is i'm just going to
change my angle
and there's a reason for that i'll cut
down towards the ear first and
[Music]
make sure once again okay when you get
down there
keep that comb on top of the ear
so here's me changing my angle look i'm
going in this direction now because
that's kind of the way that hair is
going so i like to go with the flow
don't we all
that's it so remember we're we're
getting near
the perimeter so
very small sections around the perimeter
look how much hair is in there's like
hardly any hair
in the front there
around the ear okay back of the
scissor blade against the ear and just
cut and so i'm holding the ear out of
the way back of the scissor blade
oh don't forget the h2o a little bit
more water in there you can never have
enough that just gives me control
if i comb that hair down and it's wet
it's more likely to stay there for me to
cut with my scissor
i'll just match up the other side very
very quickly
on the top more water let's make sure
that the hair is very wet and easy to
control
i need to establish a guideline so that
i know when i'm working across the head
that i'm not losing my way and i'm not
cutting shorter or longer than i should
be if i have a guideline from the start
i can follow that right through let me
show you
i have talked about the guideline in
other videos but if i separate the hair
from the crown all the way to the fringe
then i can create a guideline at the
fringe i've got this major cowlick
so what i'm going to do is tip my
fingers back
on my guideline and keep that much
longer because i want to deal with that
separately it's quite a difficult thing
to sort to cut
so we'll keep that towards the end of
this haircut
right so my guidelines in and now every
time i take a section i can see where
the short hair would be
so if i pick this up here
there you go there's the little short
here
and i'll just cut to that
so work my way forward and i'm keeping
my sections small so that it's
manageable and the scissors can get
through it
step forward again
there we go just working that guideline
it's so simple when you put the
guideline in because you can't go wrong
you know that every time you pick the
hair up you're picking up and cutting at
the right length but
as long as you keep your sections small
and manageable it's going to look neat
and tidy
now something i'll say to you if you're
enjoying this and you want to learn more
from me is that i do teach barbering on
you to me i have a scissor cutting
course and uh introduction to barbarian
course on there
so if that's the sort of thing that
you're interested in and you want to
learn more in a more structured manner
there is a link down below for that in
the description
[Music]
i'm getting near the front here and i
have been over directing it right back
so i'm lifting it right up
that's all because of that cowlick on
the front and i know that's a massive
problem when you're cutting hair
once i've cut the middle i can move over
to the side and where that little circle
is that's where there should be some
short hair which will let me know what
length to cut these side kind of
sections at
so i pick that up yeah over at the
fingertips they're short here so i use
that as my guide as i work my way
forward on this side part here
i'm just going to show you this
particular side and the other side
section i'll let you do that yourself
because it's kind of the same method
okay so short there
at the fingertips and working my way
forward
at the fringe i'm starting to over
direct back again and over direction is
when you you don't lift up straight you
kind of pull it back a little bit and
that makes it longer
yeah so because i've over directed
there's hardly anything to come off at
the very front although we're dealing
with that separately remember
and this is me very quickly kind of
joining in the
top and the sides together i'm looking
for like any little corner it's probably
better that i actually show you this on
the other side because i kind of
cut that so fast there so on the other
side let's wet it down
and just move all that hair that i've
cut out the way already and
comb down the side here okay this is
going to be a slightly better
demonstration i was cutting like a
madman on that last side there
so
pick that up
okay now what we're doing is just
looking for
long hair okay so there's some long hair
there it's like a little corner and this
is connecting
the
scissor over comb work that we did on
the sides
to the cut that we've done on the top
so keep pulling that out work your way
all the way towards the front
and that'll get you nice and joined in
now the crown i'm just going to wet that
down again okay and pull it back and
lift up now what i really want to look
for is just long hair
and
you see the short hair there and the
short hair there let's connect those two
together and that means that we don't
have anything wildly long between
the top and the back sticking out on the
crown
yeah there's quite a fair chunk there in
the middle to come off now the fringe
remember we're dealing with this
separately i'm going to cut sections in
a fan kind of shape so
so from the middle point on the top of
the head to the fringe i'm picking up
these sections and i'm going to cut some
hair and what that's going to do is it's
going to take weight out of the fringe
but not quite length at this point i'm
trying to avoid cutting length i want to
take the bulk from behind the fringe
so i'll lift these up okay take some
weight away from the fringe
and i'll tell you the reason the reason
is that because when you have a cow lick
okay the hair
will go in all sorts of directions
and it's not
best to cut that with tension to pull it
down it's best to kind of just leave it
resting on your scissor which is a
straight line
so the curve of the cowlick can form
round
and rest in a straight line
just let it take its shape let it take
its form and cut across a straight line
so i know
that
the curvature or the springiness or
whatever you want to call of the
cowlick it's just resting straight on
the comb
whereas if i was to pull that straight
and grip it in my fingers and cut it
once i release it it could go anywhere
so way better to um cut it in a relaxed
position
see there's even a little curve here a
little curl i think that's just a
natural curl it's not from the cowlick
so
before we get some real refinement on it
let's get this dried off with a vent
brush the vent brush is great because it
allows air to flow through it
so
on this area here let's try and get a
nice straight very straight line
down from the ear down to the nape of
the neck
so i'll scrape take away any just little
hairs that are sticking out and then i'm
going to pull out with my comb and let's
get this dead straight line in here
this is a style craft trimmer i'm using
by the way this is
a new addition it uh the blade's white
because it's a ceramic blade so they're
apparently very sharp
i i do quite like it it's very
very fine-tuned and
quite fast so
you can't hear it in this video because
i've muted the sound but
it sounds like a bee it's a very kind of
high pitched not high pitched but it's
like
that kind of
noise but it's a good trimmer it's good
for fine tuning so i made my straight
line and look all we've actually got
here is fluff it's hard to see but
because i was so clean with my scissor
work and my tapering
there's not a lot of work to do there
but
let's just get all the fluff off
with young men of this age you do find
that there's like a lot of kind of like
just
soft hair on their neck
so i'm getting rid of that
the other side i'm lifting this out with
a comb first
just to make sure there's no excess
weight hanging over the side and then i
am going to trim it down
so in for the straight line
there we go
happy with that
so brush all the debris away and make
sure you don't miss anything
[Music]
now we're on to trimming around the
front of the ear and the temple so you
can see what i've done here just
i like to trim all i'm looking for is
the hair that is sticking out around the
edge
remove that soft hair from his face
i can tell he's gonna have a big beard
one day
because there's a lot fluff there but
um
he's not quite there yet but i'm sure
that it will be
clear that area get all the debris away
on this side
just trim around the ear take all those
little hairs away
any excess weight
it's good these uh these t
t shaped blades
these t-shirt blades are quite good for
getting in around the ear
now one thing i'm not happy about here
is this
like
it's too heavy
so i'm gonna put my comb in and tease it
out a little bit and just take a little
bit of hair off
and that's gonna soften that line i
didn't i didn't want like
a solid line there
on the front as well like
it was a little bit dense at this site
so i'm just gonna slice it a little bit
and when you're slicing don't close the
scissor blade you know what you're doing
is you move the scissor
through the hair and just flatter it
with your thumb but don't close it so
that's just going to slice off some
excess
here's my final cut what do you think oh
that is so clean
that's i know it's my own work but that
is so clean i'm really happy with that
and the fringe is sitting really just
it's got its own curve but it's sitting
in a straight line and that's what i
want i want it to sit naturally
what do you think of the haircut do you
like it i hope you like it
i'll see you again soon in my next video
[Music]